<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Michiel Straat - Postdoctoral Researcher in Machine Learning - Bielefeld University</title>
    <link>https://michielstraat.com/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://michielstraat.com/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Michiel Straat  `2025`</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://michielstraat.com/img/avatar.jpg</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://michielstraat.com/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>SAIL</title>
      <link>https://michielstraat.com/project/sail/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://michielstraat.com/project/sail/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Artificial Intelligence is ubiquitous in our society and a key driver of economic growth. This comes with societal and technological challenges, as the increasing proliferation of current AI in society can reduce the autonomy of humans instead of supporting it. In order to address demands for transparency of AI, human agency, safety and resource-efficiency, the research project &lt;a href=&#34;https://sail.nrw&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;SAIL&lt;/a&gt; focuses on the full life-cycle of AI systems. This highly interdisciplinary research project (Core AI, humanities, social sciences and engineering) paves the way for systems that are sustainable with respect to short-term and long-term objectives and take care of their technical, cognitive and societal impact at reasonable operating costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://sail.nrw&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;SAIL.nrw&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding: Ministry of Culture and Science of the Federal State North Rhine-Westphalia&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical Physics of Learning</title>
      <link>https://michielstraat.com/project/statphys/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://michielstraat.com/project/statphys/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the deep learning era, many great results are achieved by empirical study. New deep learning methods for typical tasks in for instance computer vision, natural language processing and sound processing are tested on benchmark datasets that are publicly available and have become recognised in the respective fields. This facilitates the comparison of different approaches on these typical tasks. However, in order to make further fundamental progress, the great successes of deep learning in practice should also be supported by more theoretical results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One theoretical approach that has seen renewed interest in recent years is &lt;em&gt;The Statistical Physics of Learning&lt;/em&gt;. As the name suggests, it uses statistical physics theory to analyse Machine Learning scenarios. Statistical physics is concerned with modelling the overall properties (macroscopics) of systems that consist of many microscopic entities or particles. A neural network is a machine learning system that consists of many weights (microscopics) that connect neurons, and a configuration of weights realises a certain model with specific properties (macrosopics). The hallmark of The Statistical Physics of Learning approaches are &lt;em&gt;average case results&lt;/em&gt; of the main descriptive quantities in machine learning scenarios, i.e. typical results of the training error, the generalisation/test error as well as other summarising parameters of the state of the model, known as &lt;em&gt;order parameters&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are using the statistical physics of learning to study recent phenomena in machine learning and also to study potential new approaches for machine learning practice. We are studying typical learning behaviour of models with modern activation functions (ReLU, Leaky ReLU, GeLU) and models in dynamic environments.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reinforcement learning based control of dynamical systems</title>
      <link>https://michielstraat.com/project/dynsystemcontrol/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://michielstraat.com/project/dynsystemcontrol/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this project we employ novel AI techniques from reinforcement learning, sequence modelling and dimensionality reduction to learn complex controllers efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning for health</title>
      <link>https://michielstraat.com/project/health/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://michielstraat.com/project/health/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Machine Learning methods for among others computer vision and signal analysis have great potential for improving health care. I have been working on projects related to disease diagnosis of the eye and heart arrhythmia identification. I am currently working on projects concerning sleep disorders.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Region of Smart Factories (RoSF), Industry 4.0</title>
      <link>https://michielstraat.com/project/industry/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://michielstraat.com/project/industry/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
